So we finished the development setup over the last lectures, fixed some bugs
Bu yzden son kursta gelitirme kurulumunu bitirdik, baz hatalar dzeltdik
but now we get a working setup which is great.
ama imdi harika bir alma kuruyoruz.
Now the next step is to work on the production workflow, in my package.json file,
imdi bir sonraki adm, paketimde retim i ak zerinde almak. json dosyas, ikinci bir betie
I want to have a second script,
sahip olmak istiyorum, onu
let's name it build
ina edelim
and here I don't want to run the webpack-dev-server but the webpack. Now if I would run it like this, it
ve burada webpack-dev-server' altrmak istemiyorum. imdi byle altrrsam,
would use the setup of the development workflow.
gelitirme i aknn kurulumunu kullanrd.
We can actually do this to see the output because the development server did everything in memory,
Aslnda kty grmek iin bunu yapabiliriz nk gelitirme sunucusu bellekte her
now we can create the actual files by running npm run build, everything except the start script has to
eyi yapt, imdi npm run yapsn altrarak gerek dosyalar oluturabiliriz, start komutunun dnda her ey npm
be executed with npm run, start is the exception with npm start. So npm run build will now run
run ile altrlmal, start npm ile istisnadr bala. Dolaysyla, npm run build artk webpack'in
webpack itself and take the same config file we worked with before but now it gives us this dist
kendisini altracak ve daha nce altmz konfigrasyon dosyasn alacaktr, ancak imdi bize
folder where you now see the image file it copied and you see the javascript files here.
bu kopya dosyasn kopyaladnz grnt dosyasn greceksiniz ve javascript dosyalarn burada greceksiniz.
You see the index file it copied where it also injected our import and that is all the code we have,
thalatmz enjekte ettii dizin dosyasn gryorsunuz ve bu bizim sahip olduumuz tm
now what you can see this file already is it's not really optimized at all,
kodlar, imdi bu dosyay grebildiiniz halihazrda gerekten hi optimize
this certainly isn't the code we want to ship,
edilmiyor, bu kesinlikle gemi
so I'll delete this folder
olmak istediimiz
for now. The goal instead is to have a dedicated workflow for production which does some optimizations,
kod deil. bu yzden imdilik bu klasr silerim. Bunun yerine, baz optimizasyonlar yapan retim iin zel bir i akna sahip olmak, bu yzden yapacam
so what I'll do is I'll add a second config file, webpack.prod.config.js.
ey ikinci bir yaplandrma dosyas, web paketi ekleyeceim. prod. yaplandrma. js.
Now it won't automatically take this file into account,
imdi bu dosyay otomatik olarak hesaba katmayacak,
we will have to point at it but that's actually super simple.
ona iaret etmemiz gerekecek ama bu aslnda ok basit.
Now I'll copy the setup from the other file, from the development workflow so that we can adjust it in the
imdi, kurulum i aknda ayarlayabilmemiz iin kurulum i akndan dier
production workflow,
dosyadan kopyalayacam,
let's see what we need to adjust.
neyi ayarlamamz gerektiini grelim.
Let's start at the top,
En batan balayalm,
the dev tool, here I'll remove the eval to create more optimal source maps which are less resource intensive,
dev aracn, burada daha az kaynak younluu olan daha uygun kaynak haritalar oluturmak iin deerlendirmeyi kaldracam, daha
you can then always decide whether you want to deploy them or not
sonra bunlar datmak isteyip istemediinize her zaman karar
but it's nice to have source maps here too to quickly find some bugs in the production workflow, if there
verebilirsiniz, ancak burada kaynak haritalarnn olmas gzel Varsa, retim i aknda baz
are any.
hatalar hzlca bulmak iin.
Now the entry file still should be index.js and the output also still makes sense as it is, now
imdi giri dosyas hala dizin olmal. js ve kts da imdi olduu gibi mantkl geliyor,
the loaders, what about the loaders?
imdi ykleyiciler, ne ykleyiciler hakknda?
Well we want to apply the same transformations as in development
Biz de ayn dnmleri gelitirme aamasnda uygulamak istiyoruz,
so we don't need to touch the loaders, we'll do our work in the plugin section,
bu yzden ykleyicilere dokunmaya ihtiyacmz yok, eklenti blmnde almamz yapacaz, imdi html dosyasn
now there we have a plugin for connecting the html file and I want to keep that, what I want to do now
balamak iin bir eklentimiz var ve bunu korumak istiyorum. , imdi yapmak
is I also want to uglify my output, I want to optimize it and that actually is a plugin that's built into
istediim ey de, km uyandrmak istiyorum, onu optimize etmek istiyorum ve aslnda web paketi iine yerletirilmi
webpack,
bir
we don't need to install it.
eklentidir, yklememize gerek yok.
What I'll do is I'll simply import webpack itself into that file,
Ne yapacam sadece webpack'in kendisini bu dosyaya
so webpack via require webpack
aktaracam, bylece web paketi web
and then we can use one of the build in plugins. So down in the plugins section here, I'll add this plugin, here I'll
paketi gerektirir ve sonra eklentilerden birini kullanabiliriz. Bu yzden eklentiler blmnde, bu eklentiyi ekleyeceim,
add new webpack, optimize and there we have the uglify
burada yeni web paketi ekleyeceim, optimize edeceim ve orada uglify
js plugin. This plugin
js eklentisine sahibiz. Bu eklenti imdi
now also can be configured
de yaplandrlabilir ve her
and you can always check out the official github pages of all these plugins and loaders to do so,
zaman bu eklenti ve ykleyicilerin resmi github sayfalarn kontrol edebilirsiniz, bunu
I'll take the default setup though, so I'll remove that
yapmak iin varsaylan ayarlara gideyim, bu
and with that I got my production workflow where I also optimize the files, where I minify them to ship
yzden bunu kaldracam ve bununla birlikte retim i akm aldm Dosyalar da optimize ettiim, onlar mmkn olduunca
as little code as possible.
az kod gnderecek ekilde kltyorum.
Now to use this configuration, I need to adjust my package.json, the build scripts here where I point
imdi bu yaplandrmay kullanmak iin paketimi ayarlamalym. jpe, burada webpack'i iaret ettiim yap betikleri, varsaylan
at webpack,
konfigrasyonu kullanmak istemiyorum
I don't want to use the default config
yerine zel bir tane kullanmak istiyorum,
instead I want to use a special one, so I'll use --config, that's a flag we can pass to the webpack
bu yzden --config kullanacam, bu bir webpack komut dosyasna geebileceimiz bir bayrak. ve orada
script and there I'll point to webpack.prod.config.js file since this is in the
webpack'i iaret edeceim. prod. yaplandrma. js dosyas, bu paket ile
same folder as the package.json file,
ayn klasrde olduundan. json dosyas,
I don't need to specify any path,
herhangi bir yol
I can just specify the filename. With that I'll also add some additional options,
belirtmem gerekmiyor, sadece dosya adn belirtebilirim. Bununla birlikte, webpack yap i aknn
progress, profile, whoops, profile and colors to adjust the console output of the webpack build workflow and
konsol ktsn ayarlamak iin baz ek seenekler, ilerleme, profil, whoops, profil ve renkler ekleyeceim ve npm
I will install one additional package with npm install --save-dev,
install --save-dev ile ek bir paket kuracam, buna rimraf denir
it's called rimraf and it allows us to delete a folder or files and I want to delete the dist folder
ve Bir klasr veya dosyalar silmemize izin verir ve her yap ileminin balangcnda dist
at the start of every build process so that we create a brand new one. So I'll execute rimraf dist
klasr silmek istiyorum, bylece yepyeni bir tane oluturuyoruz. Bu yzden ben nce rimraf dist'i ve sonra iki
first and then two and signs to then run this project
tane ve bu projeyi veya buradaki komutu altrmak iin iaretlerim,
or this command here, excuse me after the deletion is done. With that,
silme bittikten sonra zr dilerim. Bununla birlikte, yeniden ina alalm, npm
let's run build again, npm run build and let's see if this gives us a nice output,
run build ve bu bize gzel bir kt verirse grelim, bana bir hata
it gives me an error because it should be --profile here as a webpack flag,
veriyor, nk bu bir webpack bayra olarak burada olmal, hadi bunu
so let's fix this,
dzeltelim, dosyay
save the file and rerun npm run build. Now with that, it's building the project we can see it here,
kaydedin ve yeniden altrn npm altrmak ina. imdi bununla birlikte, burada grebileceimiz projeyi ina ediyor,
it should succeed and it does,
baarl olmal ve bunu yapyor, yine
it gives us the dist folder still
de dis klasrn veriyor, ama
but if we have a look at the bundle file now, you see this is minified code.
imdi paket dosyasna bir baktmzda, bunun kkletirilmi kod olduunu gryorsunuz.
It's a lot of code because it includes the complete react library
ok fazla kod nk tam bir tepki ktphanesi ieriyor, ama hepsi de bu
but this is all minified and therefore optimized and the same of course in our 0.js file.
ekilde minimize edildi ve bu nedenle de bizim iin 0 oldu. js dosyas.
So now we got our dist folder and this would be what we upload to a server,
imdi bizim dist klasrmz aldk ve bu bir sunucuya, dist klasrnn
the content of the dist folder.
ieriine yklediimiz ey olurdu.
This is now our own workflow and I hope it became a bit clearer how webpack works and how you can set
Bu imdi kendi i akmz ve webpack'in nasl altn ve byle zel bir i akn nasl
up such a custom workflow.
kurabileceinizi biraz daha netletirdiini umuyoruz.